Whyte, William Foote Additional Papers /4173
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
William Foote Whyte Additional Papers
1931-1990
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Whyte, William Foote
/4173
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
8036166
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
A. Holland-Loucks, June 17, 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 03, 2016
Biographical / Historical
William Foote Whyte (June 27, 1914-July 16, 2000) was a sociologist chiefly known for his ethnographic study in urban sociology, Street Corner Society. Whyte, from an upper middle class background, showed an early interest in writing, economics and social reform. After graduating from Swarthmore College, he was selected for the Junior Fellows program, where his landmark research was done. After his research in Boston, he entered the sociology doctoral program at the University of Chicago. Street Corner Society was published by the University of Chicago Press in 1943. He spent a year teaching at the University of Oklahoma, but developed polio in 1943 and spent two years in physical therapy at the Warm Springs Foundation. Rehabilitation was only partially successful; Whyte walked with a cane for the rest of his life, and used two arm crutches in his later years. He briefly returned to the University of Chicago in 1944, then joined the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in 1948, remaining at Cornell for the remainder of his career. He worked for social reform and social change, directing his efforts toward "empowering the disenfranchized and narrowing the gap between rich and poor." He studied industrial and agricultural workers and workers' cooperatives in Venezuela, Peru, Guatemala and in the Basque region of Spain, as well as in the United States. He authored hundreds of articles and 20 books including an autobiography. He is considered a pioneer in industrial sociology.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4149 AV: "ASA Award Presentation to William Foote Whyte by Jacqueline Scheier" Audio-Visual Materials /4149: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4163: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4168: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4087: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4094: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4102: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4151: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4163: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4058: William Foote Whyte Office Records
Whyte, William Foote, 1914-2000
8036166
- pb1, photos #1-30, Missing 1,2, 1938-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  28 photographs
- pb2, 31-60 Missing 31,32,48,49,51,56,58,59,60, 1942-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  21 photographs
- pb3, photo #61-85, Missing 65-85, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- New York State School of Industrial and Business Relations Faculty 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Personally Conducted" A column by Bill Whyte, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Various Articles Relating to Bill Whyte's Engagement to Kathleen King, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "The Whyte Line" Newspaper Articles, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Lining 'Em Up" By Bill, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Misc. Newspaper Articles, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photograph from 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  1 Photograph
- Photograph of Bill Whyte, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Drawing of Bill Whyte, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Cornell Photographs, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  3 Photographs
- Manuscript v.4:no.2/4 (1933:Mar./May) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Swarthmore College student literary magazine. Contains "The Executive" by Bill Whyte
- The Swarthmore Manuscript v.6:no.1 (1935:Jan.) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Swarthmore College student literary magazine. Contains "Mary Lee" by Bill Whyte. 3 copies.
- The Swarthmore Manuscript v.6:no.2 (1935:May) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Swarthmore College student literary magazine. Contains "Political Pressure and City Budgets" by Bill Whyte. 3 copies.
- The Swarthmore Manuscript v.7:no.1 (1936:Jan.) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Swarthmore College student literary magazine. Contains "Maiden Speech" by Bill Whyte
- The Swarthmore Manuscript v.7:no.2 (1936:June) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Swarthmore College student literary magazine. Contains "Queer" by Bill Whyte
- Images digitized from the collection. (Box 2)